<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Public Policy | Zachary Dyne</title>
    <link>/tag/public-policy/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/public-policy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Public Policy</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Zachary Dyne</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Public Policy</title>
      <link>/tag/public-policy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relocation, Education, and Incentivization: Adjusting residential zoning laws to improve economic mobility in Kansas City, Missouri</title>
      <link>/post/zoninglawskcmo/kcmo-impact-zoning-laws-on-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/zoninglawskcmo/kcmo-impact-zoning-laws-on-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Economic mobility, the ability for individuals to economically fare better than their parents did, is an essential component for the continued livelihood of a city. This is especially true for Kansas City in its efforts to revitalize what was once a lively economic hub based on manufacturing and transportation to a modern metropolis fueled by technology and innovation. Recent efforts in economic development from city and state administered programs, such as the Opportunity Zone Program, the KC Rise co-investment fund, and the BioNexus KC life science development initiative, have contributed to a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcrisingmetrics.org/gdp.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;5.7% growth in real GDP&lt;/a&gt; and a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcrisingmetrics.org/MHI.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;7.8% growth in median household income from 2013 to 2017&lt;/a&gt;. While these metrics are certainly a positive indication for the city’s future, Kansas City continues to lag behind its self-identified peer cities on both metrics. Additionally, not all the development has benefited all Kansas City residents equally. Several neighborhoods, particularly those on the east side of the city, continue to experience the effects of decades of disinvestment, including underfunded public schools 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcur.org/show/up-to-date/2015-02-23/why-kansas-citys-east-side-lags-in-economic-development&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;resulting from uneven property taxes&lt;/a&gt;. According to the Stanford Education Opportunity Monitoring Project, non-poor students in the Kansas City School District perform at an average of 0.12 grades above grade level, whereas poor students perform at an average of 1.85 grades below grade level (Exhibit 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;exhibit-1&#34;&gt;Exhibit 1&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/ZoningLawsKCMO/2020-05-27-relocation-education-and-incentivization-adjusting-residential-zoning-laws-to-improve-economic-mobility-in-kansas-city-missouri_files/EDUscreenshot.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;Exhibit 1&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The red dot represents data for the Kansas City School District&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to quality K-12 education is known to have a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thebalance.com/economic-mobility-4163493&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;strong relationship with earnings later in life&lt;/a&gt;. Research by Harvard economist Raj Chetty found this to be true even after controlling for intergenerational wealth. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.citylab.com/equity/2019/08/affordable-housing-assistance-voucher-seattle-neighborhoods/595423/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chetty’s lab financed families in Seattle, Washington&lt;/a&gt; to move from Section 8 housing to areas with better public schools, which rarely had Section 8 housing, and the children in those families saw a large increase in their earnings compared to controls. While imitating Chetty’s methods appears to be a good starting point, it is not financially feasible at scale. To improve economic mobility, the City of Kansas City must create policies and programs that provide greater access to higher quality K-12 education for students from low-income families. While school vouchers or busing programs seem to be effective for a smaller number of students in the short run, a more elegant tactic possibly with further-reaching impacts involves adjusting Kansas City’s residential zoning laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because public schools are funded primarily through property taxes, those who live in areas with less valuable residential property are at a structural disadvantage in opportunities for public K-12 education. Moreover, because 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zoneomics.com/zoning-maps/missouri/kansas-city&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;much of Kansas City’s residential areas are zoned R-80&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that the minimum lot size is 80,000 square feet, there are less opportunities to develop new homes in areas with higher valued real estate. This zoning law also keeps the price of each individual lot higher, which further increase economic segregation across the city and reinforces the difference in education and lifetime earnings outcomes between poor nonpoor children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, to increase opportunities for economic mobility, the City of Kansas City should consider amending the residential zoning codes to allow for smaller single-family developments across the city. This will make moving to areas with higher valued land and higher funded public schools more accessible to lower-income families. It works towards incentivizing similar moving patters to those Chetty’s lab privately financed without requiring the city to either raise local taxes or routinely pull funding from elsewhere in the city’s annual budget to gather adequate public funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shrinking the minimum residential lot size would also have the positive effect of making buying a home more affordable across the city. Despite 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trulia.com/research/rent-vs-buy-winter-2014/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;buying a home being 66% less expensive than renting a home in Kansas City&lt;/a&gt;, home ownership has declined across the city 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bizjournals.com/kansascity/news/2016/08/18/homeownership-rental-rate-comparison.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;from 73% in 2007 to just 62% in 2016&lt;/a&gt;. This discrepancy results from an inability to afford an initial down payment on a home, despite it being a cost-saving long-term investment. If minimum lot sizes were lower, causing home prices to decline, a down payment on a home becomes more accessible to more families. Greater access to home ownership will also contributes to long-term economic mobility. Amending the zoning code is one tactic that the City of Kanas City should employ to increase opportunities for economic mobility through increased access to education and home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
