<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MBA | Zachary Dyne</title>
    <link>/category/mba/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/mba/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>MBA</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Zachary Dyne</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>MBA</title>
      <link>/category/mba/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relocation, Education, and Incentivization: Adjusting residential zoning laws to improve economic mobility in Kansas City, Missouri</title>
      <link>/post/zoninglawskcmo/kcmo-impact-zoning-laws-on-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/zoninglawskcmo/kcmo-impact-zoning-laws-on-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Economic mobility, the ability for individuals to economically fare better than their parents did, is an essential component for the continued livelihood of a city. This is especially true for Kansas City in its efforts to revitalize what was once a lively economic hub based on manufacturing and transportation to a modern metropolis fueled by technology and innovation. Recent efforts in economic development from city and state administered programs, such as the Opportunity Zone Program, the KC Rise co-investment fund, and the BioNexus KC life science development initiative, have contributed to a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcrisingmetrics.org/gdp.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;5.7% growth in real GDP&lt;/a&gt; and a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcrisingmetrics.org/MHI.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;7.8% growth in median household income from 2013 to 2017&lt;/a&gt;. While these metrics are certainly a positive indication for the city’s future, Kansas City continues to lag behind its self-identified peer cities on both metrics. Additionally, not all the development has benefited all Kansas City residents equally. Several neighborhoods, particularly those on the east side of the city, continue to experience the effects of decades of disinvestment, including underfunded public schools 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcur.org/show/up-to-date/2015-02-23/why-kansas-citys-east-side-lags-in-economic-development&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;resulting from uneven property taxes&lt;/a&gt;. According to the Stanford Education Opportunity Monitoring Project, non-poor students in the Kansas City School District perform at an average of 0.12 grades above grade level, whereas poor students perform at an average of 1.85 grades below grade level (Exhibit 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/ZoningLawsKCMO/2020-05-27-relocation-education-and-incentivization-adjusting-residential-zoning-laws-to-improve-economic-mobility-in-kansas-city-missouri_files/EDUscreenshot.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;Exhibit 1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to quality K-12 education is known to have a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thebalance.com/economic-mobility-4163493&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;strong relationship with earnings later in life&lt;/a&gt;. Research by Harvard economist Raj Chetty found this to be true even after controlling for intergenerational wealth. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.citylab.com/equity/2019/08/affordable-housing-assistance-voucher-seattle-neighborhoods/595423/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chetty’s lab financed families in Seattle, Washington&lt;/a&gt; to move from Section 8 housing to areas with better public schools, which rarely had Section 8 housing, and the children in those families saw a large increase in their earnings compared to controls. While imitating Chetty’s methods appears to be a good starting point, it is not financially feasible at scale. To improve economic mobility, the City of Kansas City must create policies and programs that provide greater access to higher quality K-12 education for students from low-income families. While school vouchers or busing programs seem to be effective for a smaller number of students in the short run, a more elegant tactic possibly with further-reaching impacts involves adjusting Kansas City’s residential zoning laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because public schools are funded primarily through property taxes, those who live in areas with less valuable residential property are at a structural disadvantage in opportunities for public K-12 education. Moreover, because 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zoneomics.com/zoning-maps/missouri/kansas-city&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;much of Kansas City’s residential areas are zoned R-80&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that the minimum lot size is 80,000 square feet, there are less opportunities to develop new homes in areas with higher valued real estate. This zoning law also keeps the price of each individual lot higher, which further increase economic segregation across the city and reinforces the difference in education and lifetime earnings outcomes between poor nonpoor children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, to increase opportunities for economic mobility, the City of Kansas City should consider amending the residential zoning codes to allow for smaller single-family developments across the city. This will make moving to areas with higher valued land and higher funded public schools more accessible to lower-income families. It works towards incentivizing similar moving patters to those Chetty’s lab privately financed without requiring the city to either raise local taxes or routinely pull funding from elsewhere in the city’s annual budget to gather adequate public funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shrinking the minimum residential lot size would also have the positive effect of making buying a home more affordable across the city. Despite 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trulia.com/research/rent-vs-buy-winter-2014/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;buying a home being 66% less expensive than renting a home in Kansas City&lt;/a&gt;, home ownership has declined across the city 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bizjournals.com/kansascity/news/2016/08/18/homeownership-rental-rate-comparison.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;from 73% in 2007 to just 62% in 2016&lt;/a&gt;. This discrepancy results from an inability to afford an initial down payment on a home, despite it being a cost-saving long-term investment. If minimum lot sizes were lower, causing home prices to decline, a down payment on a home becomes more accessible to more families. Greater access to home ownership will also contributes to long-term economic mobility. Amending the zoning code is one tactic that the City of Kanas City should employ to increase opportunities for economic mobility through increased access to education and home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Overview of the Willamette MBA Community Grant Program SQL Database</title>
      <link>/post/agsmgrantsql/agsmgrantssql/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/agsmgrantsql/agsmgrantssql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite courses I took during my time at Atkinson was &lt;em&gt;GSMDS5003: Data Engineering&lt;/em&gt;, taught by the one and only Prof. Henry Bi. We not only learned how to write SQL code but also about the fundamentals of database design, including entity relational (ER) modeling, standardization, and normalization. Learning the structure of well designed databases made learning to retrieve data via SQL a fairly straitforward extension. The course&amp;rsquo;s final project was to create a database of our own using Microsoft Access, so I decided to use this opportunity to solve a different problem I was dealing with: the information scattered throughout the Google Drive of the Willamette MBA Community Grant Program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;willamette-mba-community-grant-program&#34;&gt;Willamette MBA Community Grant Program&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agsmgrants.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Willamette MBA Community Grant Program&lt;/a&gt; is the only 100% student-administered grantmaking program in the US and provides funding opportunities for nonprofit or social service organizations serving Oregon&amp;rsquo;s 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://geology.com/county-map/oregon.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Marion, Polk, and/or Yamhill counties&lt;/a&gt;. As students facilitating multiple rounds of grantee applications by reviewing organizational and operational metrics while following up on the results of projects from previous funding cycles, it was getting difficult to keep track of all of the information we needed. As the project manager and lead financial data analyst, the disorganization made creating tools for internal communication, financial statement analysis, and risk modeling particularly tedious. Additionally, because it is completely student-run, the program experiences 100% annual turnover, with the exception of the two faculty instructors. This makes organizing institutional knowledge all the more difficult yet essential. Seems like a problem an Access SQL database could solve!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;database-overview&#34;&gt;Database Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal in creating this database was to make it as flexable as possible to adapt to future itrations of the program. The Grant Program only just finished its fourth year and there are many things that could hypothetically happen that haven&amp;rsquo;t yet. As such, the database seems a bit redundant (in SQL-talk: it has more many-to-many relationships than initally seems necessary). For example, an &lt;em&gt;EnrollIn&lt;/em&gt; relationship needs its own table since it is hypothetically possible for a student to enroll in the course more than once (they coud be a JD/MBA or an MBA-for-Life student). If we just assumed that each student will enroll in the course only once, &lt;em&gt;EnrollIn&lt;/em&gt; could just be a column in the &lt;em&gt;Student&lt;/em&gt;  table. Feel free to check out the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1rOdZmnAYQa-UH4V_KDCOjGDaF2aHaYjl/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;full project description&lt;/a&gt; for all of the database requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I can&amp;rsquo;t share the content of many tables due to privacy reasons, I can share the database&amp;rsquo;s relationship diagrams as a proof of concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;entity-relation-model&#34;&gt;Entity Relation Model&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/AGSMGrantSQL/2020-05-23-an-overview-of-the-willamette-mba-community-grant-program-sql-database_files/ERDModel.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;ERD Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;access-relational-diagram&#34;&gt;Access Relational Diagram&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/AGSMGrantSQL/2020-05-23-an-overview-of-the-willamette-mba-community-grant-program-sql-database_files/AccessRelation.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;Access Relational&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;hey-it-works&#34;&gt;Hey, it works!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sample problem: &lt;em&gt;List the organization name, project name, description, and amount recieved for each project operated by an organization who has operate more than one project. Provide the list in descending order by amount.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/AGSMGrantSQL/2020-05-23-an-overview-of-the-willamette-mba-community-grant-program-sql-database_files/SampleCode.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;Sample Code&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/AGSMGrantSQL/2020-05-23-an-overview-of-the-willamette-mba-community-grant-program-sql-database_files/SampleQ.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;Sample Q&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun working on this project since it combines two of my primary interests: data science and nonprofit management. Thank you to Prof. Henry Bi for your guidance and encouragement along the way! If you&amp;rsquo;re interested to learn more about the Willamette MBA Community Grant Program, check out the recently published 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5d96678c577c9008fd68696b/t/5eb30597c5e14117f3481700/1588790698192/WUMBA_PICI_Y4_AnnualReport2020.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2019-2020 Annual Report&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Analysis of HP&#39;s Quarterly Stock Return</title>
      <link>/post/hpstock/hp-stock/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/hpstock/hp-stock/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#project-background&#34;&gt;Project Background&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#data-understanding&#34;&gt;Data Understanding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#holt-linear-smoothing&#34;&gt;Holt Linear Smoothing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#arima&#34;&gt;ARIMA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#method-comparison-to-actual-results&#34;&gt;Method Comparison to actual results&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-did-we-learn&#34;&gt;What did we learn?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;project-background&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to take a course on time series economic forecasting during my MBA program. This was certainly one of the more challenging data-related courses given how many moving parts are invovled in time series analysis and how much it deviates from my quantitative social science background. All the new content made it all the more valuable. I also appreciated that each of the course’s assignments were done in groups and I was fortunate to work with Roxanne Adams and Matt Stone throughout the semester. The course’s final project involved finding a time series dataset and identifying which forecasting methods work best at predicting future events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a big fan of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://business-science.github.io/tidyquant/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;tidyquant&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package and its ability to fetch data directly from Yahoo! Finance without having to dowload a .csv from the internet, I persuaded our group to use it to analyze HP’s stock return. This also solved a classic student problem of having to switch file directories when sharing the file among our group (this was before I really knew how to use Github).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why HP and why stock retrun? As a consumer it would appear as if a large part of the company’s sales come from printers, ink, and tonor, which are items that are generally being replaced by cloud services (Google Drive for indivdiuals and AWS for enterprises) in the “information sharing” market. Of course, they also sell computers and a large suite of enterprise technology services. Based on that admitidely unresearched assumption it would seem at first that HP’s attractiveness as an investment would change quite a bit over time. While neither I nor my teammates would call ourselves financial market gurus, we were curious to see how these changing market trends would be refleceted in HP’s quarterly return over time. Plus, HP is a big employer in the Oregon tech community with offices in Corvallis and just across the boarder in Vancouver, Washington. We already used Intel’s in a class example and we had to choose something. After we started working on this project we discovered that Xerox was working on a bid for a hostile takeover of HP, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/sergeiklebnikov/2020/01/06/xerox-secures-24-billion-for-hostile-takeover-bid-of-hp/#6c80dd81b4d6&#34;&gt;which was recently secured&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;package-and-data-setup&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Package and Data Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Package Setup

library(tidyverse) # for data wrangling and analysis
library(fpp2) # for forecasting functions
library(tidyquant) # for stock price data
library(ggthemes) # for plot themes
library(ggplot2); theme_set(theme_economist_white()) # set plot theme to resemble the Economist

## Data Setup
# Fetch HP and S&amp;amp;P500 Quartely Return from 2000 - 2017

Rb &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;^GSPC&amp;quot; %&amp;gt;% # fetch S&amp;amp;P500
    tq_get(get  = &amp;quot;stock.prices&amp;quot;,
           from = &amp;quot;2000-01-01&amp;quot;, to = &amp;quot;2018-01-01&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
    tq_transmute(select     = adjusted, 
                 mutate_fun = periodReturn, 
                 period     = &amp;quot;quarterly&amp;quot;, 
                 col_rename = &amp;quot;SP500&amp;quot;)

Ra &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;HPQ&amp;quot; %&amp;gt;% # fetch HP&amp;#39;s stock price  
    tq_get(get  = &amp;quot;stock.prices&amp;quot;,
           from = &amp;quot;2000-01-01&amp;quot;, to = &amp;quot;2018-01-01&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
    tq_transmute(select     = adjusted, 
                 mutate_fun = periodReturn, 
                 period     = &amp;quot;quarterly&amp;quot;, 
                 col_rename = &amp;quot;HPQ&amp;quot;)

RaRb &amp;lt;- left_join(Ra, Rb, by = c(&amp;quot;date&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;date&amp;quot;)) # bind HP and S&amp;amp;P500 by date

RaRb &amp;lt;- RaRb %&amp;gt;% # paste quarterly and yearly labels together for plotting
  mutate(Year = substr(date, 1, 4)) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(Quarter = rep(rep(1:4), 72/4)) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(QuarterLab = paste(&amp;quot;Q&amp;quot;, Quarter, sep = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(Period = paste(Year, QuarterLab, sep = &amp;quot;:&amp;quot;))

RaRb1 &amp;lt;- RaRb %&amp;gt;% # create training dataset, extracting years 2015-2017. 
  mutate(QuarterID = (1:length(HPQ))) %&amp;gt;% #We will test the model with those years at the end
  filter(QuarterID &amp;lt; (length(HPQ)-11))
tail(RaRb1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;kable-table&#34;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;HPQ&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;SP500&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Quarter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;QuarterLab&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;QuarterID&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2013-09-30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;-0.1481195&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0468598&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Q3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2013:Q3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;55&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2013-12-31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.3400305&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0992001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Q4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2013:Q4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014-03-31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.1620944&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0129737&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Q1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014:Q1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014-06-30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0457355&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0469413&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Q2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014:Q2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014-09-30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0576499&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0061524&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Q3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014:Q3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014-12-31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.1359744&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;0.0439134&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Q4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2014:Q4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-understanding&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data Understanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;RaRb1 %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(x=date, y = HPQ)) + 
  geom_line(size = 1.1) +
  scale_x_date(labels = RaRb$Period, breaks = RaRb$date) +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 90, hjust = 1, size = 6)) +
  ggtitle(&amp;quot;Hewlett-Packard Quarterly Stock Return&amp;quot;, subtitle = &amp;quot;2000:Q1 - 2014:Q4&amp;quot;) + 
  ylab(&amp;quot;Quarterly Percent Return&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/HPStock/2019-12-19-an-analysis-of-hp-s-quarterly-stock-return_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see no consistent seasonality and no consistant upward or downard trend. At first glance there does appear to be a dip in returns in each Q3, but there are a few counterexamples. There is a cyclical pattern in return wiht an upward trend from 2002-2005, downard from 2006-2011, and up again from 2011-2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;which-forecasting-methods-might-work&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Which forecasting methods might work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is no harm in trying everything and seeing what sticks, the patterns in the data can provide insights into what forecasting methods are most likely to work. Becasue there is no strong ternd or seasonality, a linear forecasting method wouldn’t make much sense. An Error-Trend-Seasonal (ETS) method wouldn’t work because they work best for seaonal forecasting. For consistency, we did try these methods to see what would happen, and indeed they violated model assumptions and/or performed poorly. I won’t include them here to save space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lead us to two possible leads: Holt Exponential Smoothing to measure trend and level and ARIMA (autoregresssive integrating moving average, best for nonseasonal data).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;holt-linear-smoothing&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holt Linear Smoothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;h &amp;lt;- holt(RaRb1$HPQ)
hd &amp;lt;- holt(RaRb1$HPQ, damped = T, phi = 0.95)
hd2 &amp;lt;- holt(RaRb1$HPQ, damped = T, phi = 0.8)
autoplot(ts(RaRb1$HPQ)) +
  autolayer(h, PI = F, series = &amp;quot; Regular Holt&amp;quot;) +
  autolayer(hd, PI = F, series = &amp;quot;Damped Holt (high phi)&amp;quot;) +
  autolayer(hd2, PI = F, series = &amp;quot;Damped Holt (low phi)&amp;quot;) +
  ggtitle(&amp;quot;Holt and Damped Holt Forecasts&amp;quot;,
          subtitle = &amp;quot;Hewlett-Packard Quarterly Stock Return&amp;quot;) +
  theme(legend.title = element_blank())&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/HPStock/2019-12-19-an-analysis-of-hp-s-quarterly-stock-return_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The damped methods produce fairly similar results. This is likely becasue there is no trend to really dampen, wich is the idea behind the dampening parameter. To simplify things, we just used the regular Holt method for our analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(h)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## Forecast method: Holt&amp;#39;s method
## 
## Model Information:
## Holt&amp;#39;s method 
## 
## Call:
##  holt(y = RaRb1$HPQ) 
## 
##   Smoothing parameters:
##     alpha = 0.0554 
##     beta  = 1e-04 
## 
##   Initial states:
##     l = 0.089 
##     b = 0 
## 
##   sigma:  0.2112
## 
##      AIC     AICc      BIC 
## 64.92805 66.03916 75.39977 
## 
## Error measures:
##                       ME      RMSE       MAE      MPE    MAPE      MASE
## Training set -0.01380629 0.2040401 0.1529902 134.1629 176.444 0.7198957
##                     ACF1
## Training set -0.07826283
## 
## Forecasts:
##    Point Forecast      Lo 80     Hi 80      Lo 95     Hi 95
## 61     0.03984102 -0.2308247 0.3105068 -0.3741065 0.4537886
## 62     0.03980209 -0.2312804 0.3108846 -0.3747828 0.4543870
## 63     0.03976317 -0.2317369 0.3112632 -0.3754603 0.4549867
## 64     0.03972424 -0.2321942 0.3116427 -0.3761392 0.4555877
## 65     0.03968531 -0.2326525 0.3120231 -0.3768194 0.4561900
## 66     0.03964639 -0.2331115 0.3124043 -0.3775009 0.4567936
## 67     0.03960746 -0.2335715 0.3127864 -0.3781837 0.4573986
## 68     0.03956853 -0.2340323 0.3131693 -0.3788678 0.4580048
## 69     0.03952960 -0.2344939 0.3135531 -0.3795532 0.4586124
## 70     0.03949068 -0.2349564 0.3139377 -0.3802399 0.4592212&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;checkresiduals(h)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/HPStock/2019-12-19-an-analysis-of-hp-s-quarterly-stock-return_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
##  Ljung-Box test
## 
## data:  Residuals from Holt&amp;#39;s method
## Q* = 5.3108, df = 6, p-value = 0.5046
## 
## Model df: 4.   Total lags used: 10&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accuracy Metrics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RMSE = 0.204&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MAE 0.1529&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality Metrics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No autocorrelation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Residual mean is roughly zero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Residuals seem indepenent with constant variance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Residuals are mostly normally distriuted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However the p-value is farily high at 0.5046&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe an ARIMA will perform better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;arima&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;ARIMA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s try an ARIMA method&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;HPQArima1 &amp;lt;- RaRb1 %&amp;gt;%
  select(HPQ) %&amp;gt;%
  auto.arima(lambda = BoxCox.lambda(RaRb1$HPQ)) # auto.arima() selects the optimal constant values

summary(HPQArima1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Series: . 
## ARIMA(0,0,0) with non-zero mean 
## Box Cox transformation: lambda= 0.7043195 
## 
## Coefficients:
##          mean
##       -1.3862
## s.e.   0.0523
## 
## sigma^2 estimated as 0.1672:  log likelihood=-30.97
## AIC=65.93   AICc=66.14   BIC=70.12
## 
## Training set error measures:
##                      ME      RMSE       MAE      MPE    MAPE      MASE
## Training set 0.01521414 0.1974573 0.1497182 102.6973 105.691 0.7044997
##                     ACF1
## Training set -0.09284311&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;HPQArima1Fcast &amp;lt;- HPQArima1 %&amp;gt;%
  forecast(h=10) # forecast 10 periods
HPQArima1Fcast&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##    Point Forecast      Lo 80     Hi 80      Lo 95     Hi 95
## 61    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 62    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 63    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 64    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 65    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 66    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 67    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 68    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 69    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934
## 70    0.004924653 -0.2209981 0.2652703 -0.4176718 0.4705934&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## autoplot forecast
HPQArima1 %&amp;gt;%
  forecast(h=11) %&amp;gt;%
  autoplot()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/HPStock/2019-12-19-an-analysis-of-hp-s-quarterly-stock-return_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;checkresiduals(HPQArima1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/HPStock/2019-12-19-an-analysis-of-hp-s-quarterly-stock-return_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
##  Ljung-Box test
## 
## data:  Residuals from ARIMA(0,0,0) with non-zero mean
## Q* = 3.9186, df = 9, p-value = 0.9167
## 
## Model df: 1.   Total lags used: 10&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accuracy Metrics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RMSE = 0.1974573&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MAE = 0.1497182&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality Metrics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Residuals appear to have a mean of zero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Residuals vary independently and constantly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;REsiduals are mostly normally distributed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No evidence of autocorrelation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;p-value = 0.9167&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARIMA(0,0,0) essentially predicts that the return will be roughly zero over a long enough perido of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;method-comparison-to-actual-results&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method Comparison to actual results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both models preseted satisfy all residual assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holt’s method has a lower RMSE and MAE, meaning it generally performs bettere at predicting actual events, and is easier to interpret. Here is the Holt forecast plotted on top of the actaul values for 2014:Q1-2017:Q4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;autoplot(ts(RaRb$HPQ)) +
  autolayer(h, PI = F) +
  ggtitle(&amp;quot;Hewlett-Packard Quarterly Stock Return&amp;quot;, 
          subtitle = &amp;quot;2000:Q1 - 2017:Q4 | Actual vs Holt Forecasted&amp;quot;) +
  ylab(&amp;quot;Quarterly Percent Return&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/HPStock/2019-12-19-an-analysis-of-hp-s-quarterly-stock-return_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-9-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-did-we-learn&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What did we learn?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in long term trends, this isn’t too bad. HP has remained a somewhat attractive investment with a return just above zero. Of course, this is a fairly simplistic method of forecsating the stock market. Did we find anything remarkably insightful in our data? Not really. However, for a final project in an introduction to time series modeling course, it was fun way to practice some of our newfound skills. With more time, I’m looking forwrd to playing around more with &lt;em&gt;tidyquant&lt;/em&gt; and time series methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
